<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Phinehas, or, The common duty of all men, and the special duty of magistrates, to be zealous and active in the execution of laws against scandalous sins and debauchery and of that in particular, against prophane cursing and swearing.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93859</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5433A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184628</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077647</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077647</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151756</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93859)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151756)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2275:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Phinehas, or, The common duty of all men, and the special duty of magistrates, to be zealous and active in the execution of laws against scandalous sins and debauchery and of that in particular, against prophane cursing and swearing.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 3-16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Smith, at the Angel near Lincolns-Inn Back-gate. And are to be sold by Richard Baldwin, at the Oxford-Armes in Warwick-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles, California.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swearing --  Great Britain --  Law and legislation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151756:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PHINEHAS: OR, THE Common Duty of all Men.</p>
            <p>And the Special <hi>Duty of Magiſtrates,</hi> To be Zealous and Active in the <hi>Execution of Laws</hi> AGAINST Scandalous Sins and Debauchery; And of that in Particular, againſt Prophane <hi>Curſing and Swearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Smith,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> near <hi>Lincolns-Inn</hi> Back-Gate. And are to be Sold by <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> at the <hi>Oxford-Armes</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:151756:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151756:2"/>
            <head>PHINEHAS: OR, The Common Duty of all Men, AND THE Special Duty of Magiſtrates, Concerning the Execution of the LAWS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THAT <hi>Sobriety, Vertue,</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> are abſolutely neceſſary in a People, for the <hi>Good and Well-Being of a Community,</hi> as they are in particular Perſons for their own Well-Being; and, on the contrary, that <hi>Luxury, Vice,</hi> and <hi>Impiety,</hi> are as Pernicious and Deſtructive to both; is not only certain in it ſelf, but eaſily apparent to any Man of Reaſon and unprejudiced Judgment, who will apply his Mind to a ſerious Conſideration of the Nature, Effects, and Conſequences thereof; of the Experience of all Ages, legible in the Hiſtories of all Nations; and of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Perſons and People moſt Fam'd for Wiſdom in all Nations of the World, legible in their Laws, and other Writings.</p>
            <p>And for the Securing and Procuring of this <hi>Good,</hi> and for Avoiding or Removing the contrary <hi>Evil,</hi> that GOOD LAWS are no leſs neceſſary for Communities, than Good Inſtructions for particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Perſons, is likewiſe certain in it ſelf, and alſo eaſie to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, both from the Conſideration of the Nature of Man corrupted and prone to Evil, and from common Experience, and the Judgment of the Wiſeſt of Men in all Ages and Parts of the World.</p>
            <p>Again, It is as certain and evident, that <hi>no Laws,</hi> be they never ſo Good, are <hi>ſufficient</hi> of themſelves for theſe Purpoſes, <hi>unleſs</hi> they be duly and conſtantly <hi>Executed:</hi> Nay, That it is better to have none at all, than not to have them Executed: For, as the Violation of Laws is a Contempt of Authority, ſo the Neglect of the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution is a Proſtitution of it, expoſing the Government, and tending
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151756:3"/>to the Diſſolution of it, and to habituate and harden the People the more in Wickedneſs and Diſobedience.</p>
            <p>And from hence it is very plain, That ſuch as have little Care or Concern for the EXECUTION of the LAWS, for the Purpoſes afore ſaid, have but little Care or Concern for the <hi>Good</hi> of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, or <hi>Good Will</hi> to it; and, therefore, do not deſerve any Reſpect from their Countrey, but to be look'd upon as unnatural <hi>Beaſts</hi> and <hi>Monſters,</hi> unworthy to Live in a <hi>Civil Society,</hi> and much more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be Choſen into any Place of <hi>Authority</hi> or <hi>Honour</hi> in it; as, on the other ſide, they who are Studious, Active and Induſtrious to promote the <hi>Execution</hi> of <hi>Good Laws,</hi> are juſtly to be accounted and eſteemed, by all Men, as principal <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors</hi> to their Countrey, and as beſt deſerving <hi>Preferment, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> amongſt them: and all ſuch as are for the Choice or Promotion of any Perſons, upon other Conſiderations, as of their Eſtates or Treatments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without Regard to this, are to be look'd upon as <hi>Brutes, Suckers,</hi> or <hi>Evil Members</hi> in the Community.</p>
            <p>This, Natural Reaſon, Experience, and common Humanity, do dictate to us: But we are to remember, that this is a <hi>Chriſtian State,</hi> and if we be what we profeſs, ſincere and honeſt Chriſtians indeed, we muſt know, that a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is a Man and more, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> as far tranſcending that of a meer Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Man, as that which is peculiar to Man doth that which is common to him with Brutes, and filling him with Reverence and Devotion to God, and Zeal for his Honour and Service, and with Love and Good Will to Men, and a Readineſs to all Acts of Charity and Benificence.</p>
            <p>A <hi>good Chriſtian</hi> will be good in all Relations; a good Parent, a good Child; a good Maſter, a good Servant; a good Magiſtrate, a good Subject; a good Neighbour, a good Citizen, and a good Common-Wealths Man. He that is not ſo, doth Diſhonour his Profeſſion, and ſhall receive the greater Damnation for that, beſides his other Sins. And he that is ſo indeed, will not think it enough to live peaceably, and enjoy the Benefit of the Protection of the Laws; but will always deſire, and will likewiſe endeavour, the Good of his Countrey, when-ever he is called to it; and then, certainly, is he implicitly call'd to it, when-ever he meets with any <hi>Opportunity</hi> to ſerve it, and particularly in this Matter, of Promoting the <hi>Execution</hi> of the <hi>Laws.</hi> Then is the Admonition, <hi>What-ever thy Hand findeth to do, do it with thy might,</hi> Eccleſ. 9.10. to be remembred and put in Practice. And, <hi>Curſed be he that doth the Work of the Lord deceitfully,</hi> Jer. 48.10. to be remembred for a Warning. This all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151756:3"/>are obliged to do, as I ſhall further ſhew hereafter; but becauſe the MAGISTRATES are, moreover, under other and more ſpecial Obligations by the <hi>Places</hi> they hold, and the <hi>Oaths</hi> they take, I ſhall firſt conſider thoſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Office of Magiſtrates</hi> is a <hi>Great Truſt</hi> repoſed in them, firſt and originally by <hi>God</hi> Himſelf. They are his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> for the Good of his People, and he will require an Account of them, how they have behaved themſelves in the Diſcharge of it. Though he permits the Choice to Men, yet will he Judge all at laſt. And therefore they may do well to have much in their Minds the Charge of <hi>Jehoſhaphet</hi> to his Judges, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 19.6. <hi>Take heed what ye do: for ye judge not for Man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the Judgment. Wherefore, now let the Fear of the Lord be upon you. Take heed, and do it: for there is no Iniquity with the Lord our God, nor Reſpect of Perſons, nor taking of Bribes.</hi> v. 9. <hi>Thus ſhall ye do in the Fear of the Lord, faithfully, and with a perfect heart.</hi> v. 11. <hi>Deal couragiouſly, and the Lord ſhall be with the Good.</hi> But more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately,</p>
            <p>It is a <hi>Publick Truſt</hi> repoſed in them <hi>by their Countrey, by the Hand of their Prince.</hi> And if the Non-Performance, or Neglect, or Breach of a Truſt between Man and Man be a thing ſo odious and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, as it is commonly reputed, certainly the Neglect of a Publick Truſt, repoſed in them by their King and Countrey, is really much more to be condemned.</p>
            <p>The due Performance and Diſcharge of this Truſt and Charge is a principle Part of the <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Fidelity</hi> which they owe to their King and Countrey, and of true <hi>Loyalty.</hi> And therefore, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever pretend to thoſe things, and refuſe or neglect the compleat Diſcharge of this Truſt, when Occaſion is offered, are meer Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to what they are not, and are to be eſteem'd no better than <hi>Knaves</hi> and <hi>Cheats,</hi> who ſeek to ſerve themſelves, under ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Pretences and Appearances. And ſuch are all who pretend highly to thoſe things, and yet, at the ſame time, make no Scruple to tranſgreſs the <hi>Laws,</hi> whether they be in any Authority or not; they are plainly, either <hi>Knaves,</hi> that would abuſe both their King and Countrey by their Pretences; or Fools, that underſtand not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or what they do; and do not deſerve any Reſpect from any Men of Senſe, that are Lovers of their Countrey.</p>
            <p>Thus far the very <hi>Acceptance</hi> of ſuch an Office of Truſt doth oblige; but with us they are moreover obliged by <hi>Solemn Oath;</hi> nay, doubly obliged; for they muſt take <hi>Two Oaths</hi> at their Entrance upon their Office: The <hi>Oath of Allegiance or Fidelity,</hi> whereby that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151756:4"/>Allegiance and Fidelity which they were before obliged to keep and perform, as they are Members of the Community, they are now farther obliged, by <hi>Solemn Oath,</hi> to keep and perform inviolable: And every Tranſgreſſion or Neglect of this Duty becomes doubly culpable by Breach of <hi>Duty,</hi> and by Breach of <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Perjury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Perjury</hi> is double too: For beſides the more general <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> there is another <hi>Oath</hi> more eſpecially <hi>concerning the Office of Juſtice of the Peace,</hi> which hath been anciently to the like Effect that now it is. It comprehends in few Words a Summary of their Duty; as followeth,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſhall Swear, That as Iuſtice of the Peace in the County of</hi> N. <hi>in all</hi> Articles <hi>in the King's</hi> Commiſſion <hi>to you directed, You ſhall do Equal Right to the Poor, and to the Rich, after your Cunning, Wit, and Power, and after the Laws and Cuſtoms of the Realm, and Statutes thereof made,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In which Words, there are three things obſervable. 1. The <hi>Duty, or the Matter</hi> of the Obligation. And that is 1. In General, to do Right, or Juſtice. 2. More eſpecially to do Equal Right, without Reſpect of Perſons, to the Poor, and to the Rich. 2. The <hi>Extent or Limitation</hi> of it; and that is Threefold. 1. Within a certain County. It is limited to the County expreſſed in the Commiſſion; but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to the whole Countrey. And the Obligation is of the ſame extent with the Authority. 2. Within the Articles of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. It is in all the Articles in the King's Commiſſion; but limited to them. 3. In the Rule; it muſt be after the <hi>Laws, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms,</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> of the Realm. And, 3. The <hi>Manner,</hi> and that is after the Cunning, Wit, and Power of the Juſtice, according to the beſt of his Underſtanding, Skill, and Ability.</p>
            <p>What is more briefly and ſummarily comprized in the <hi>Oath,</hi> is more fully and particularly expreſſed and ſet out in the <hi>Commiſſion;</hi> which begins thus;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Know, Ye, That we have aſſigned you joyntly and ſeverally, and every one of you, our Iuſtices, to conſerve our Peace in the County of</hi> N. <hi>and to keep and cauſe to be kept in our ſaid County, as well within Liberties as without, All Ordinances and Statutes made for the Good of our Peace, and the Conſervation thereof, and for the quiet Rule and Government of our People, in all and every the Articles thereof, according to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151756:4"/>Force, Form, and Effect thereof: And to Chaſtiſe and Puniſh all Perſons in our ſaid County offending againſt the Form of theſe Ordinances or Statutes, or any of them, as according to the Form of theſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Statutes is to be done,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Here, in the Beginning of the <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> we have <hi>the End</hi> for which it is Granted; and that is, <hi>to keep the Peace,</hi> and <hi>to keep and cauſe to be kept All Ordinances and Statutes,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>the Means,</hi> by which they are to cauſe them to be kept; and that is, <hi>to Chaſtiſe and Puniſh All Perſons Offending.</hi> But, firſt, they are to keep them <hi>Themſelves;</hi> and that is a good Means to induce others to do the like, by giving them a good <hi>Example.</hi> But ſuch <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> as make no Scruple to break any of the LAWS, which they are Sworn to keep, and to cauſe all others to keep, do in effect teach all others to deſpiſe the Government, and their own Authority; and to make light of their Oaths, and ſo, as much as in them is, diſſolve all the Bond and Tyes of Government; and are therefore utterly unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to hold any Place in it. The Conſequence of Occaſions to the People, to ſhew any Diſ-reſpect to the Publick Authority, though it be but in Inſtances of what may be thought leſſer Offences at the firſt, is more pernicious to any Government, than the Breaches of the Laws in greater Inſtances, when duly puniſhed.</p>
            <p>But as they muſt firſt keep them <hi>Themſelves,</hi> ſo muſt they cauſe them to be kept by <hi>Others,</hi> by Puniſhment of <hi>All Perſons Offending.</hi> This is that Equal Right to the Poor, and to the Rich, that Impartial Juſtice which they oblige themſelves to do by Solemn Oath. It muſt be done upon All Offenders, <hi>Omnes in Comitatu praedicto delinquentes;</hi> All, without Exception. All are ſubject to theſe Laws, be their Eſtate or Quality what it will. And if I be intruſted by the King, and Sworn to God, to Execute the Laws, I muſt Execute them upon All Perſons, be they who they will, Civil, Military, or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, who preſume to tranſgreſs them, and thereby ſubject them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Authority with which I am inveſted and intruſted. Be he my Equal, or be he my Superior in any other Reſpect, yet if he trangreſs theſe LAWS, which I am bound to Execute, and within the Limits and Extent of my Juriſdiction, I am bound to Execute them upon him; though, in all other Reſpects, I muſt treat him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Quality. Even <hi>Priviledge of Parliament</hi> extends not to ſome Crimes. And though the final Determination may not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to me, yet if any mean Acts, ſuch as Enquiry, Examination, Commitment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in order to further Puniſhment, do, I muſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151756:5"/>the Laws ſo far as I am authorized. And here it may be noted, That <hi>Partiality,</hi> or wilful Connivance, or Indulgence to any in their Offences, againſt the Laws, is of like evil Conſequence with the Magiſtrates taking Liberty to themſelves to tranſgreſs. It encourages hope of Impunity, and ſo tends to fruſtrate the very End of Puniſhment, which is, to deterr others from the like Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences.</p>
            <p>If theſe things were well conſidered, Men would neither be ſo forward to undertake ſo great and weighty a Charge, much greater than they are aware of, as many are; nor ſo eaſily ſatisfie themſelves in any Neglect of their Duty, after they are once ſo engaged in it, as too many do. If they did well conſider it, they would either never be perſwaded to ingage in it, or reſolve to diſcharge it faithfully, whatever it coſt them; and, to that end, ſpare no Pains, by Study, by Converſation, and by conſtant and diligent Attendance to Buſineſs with others, to qualifie themſelves for it. For though no Man is obliged further than he is able, ſo that he be ſincere and faithful in doing the beſt he can: yet the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> ſuppoſeth a Competence of Knowledge and Skill in all that are Commiſſioned: And they that are conſcious to themſelves, that they are not in ſome ſort qualified, and yet will undertake it, will have nothing to excuſe them, if they commit any great Miſcarriage: But ſuch, as with a good Deſign to ſerve God and their Countrey, do ingage in it, and though ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of ſome Deficience, and that they are not ſo compleatly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified as they would be, yet are diligent, both to improve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to diſcharge their Duty upon all Occaſions, in the beſt manner that they can, need not doubt of the Acceptance and Bleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God upon them. And this I muſt ſay, for their <hi>Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> if they be Perſons of Conſcience and Religion, and undertake it with pure Intention, and good Deſign, and with Reſolution to be Faithful in it, and do act accordingly, that as they do at the ſame Inſtant enter into a new Relation to Almighty God, and become his Miniſters, ſo they are admitted to the Priviledge of a Special Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; and, beſides a ſpecial Providence over them here, if they continue Faithful to the laſt, will have a ſpecial Reward of their Fidelity hereafter.</p>
            <p>Beſides <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> there are other inferiour Officers; as <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables,</hi> and <hi>Church-Wardens,</hi> who are under ſpecial Obligations by <hi>Oath,</hi> to be aſſiſting in this Buſineſs. But there is no occaſion to ſay any thing of them in particular, more than this, That their Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glects are aggravated by an Addition of <hi>Perjury.</hi> And, therefore, to return to the common Obligations upon All;</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151756:5"/>
            <p>If Good Laws be neceſſary, if <hi>Execution</hi> of them be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, if <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> be neceſſary for that, then muſt alſo Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Offences committed againſt the Laws be neceſſary to the <hi>Magiſtrates:</hi> And becauſe they are ſeldom committed in the Preſence of <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> due INFORMATION by thoſe who have ſufficient Knowledge of any ſuch, is likewiſe neceſſary, as the very Foundation upon which the <hi>due Execution</hi> of the Laws doth depend. From whence it doth follow plainly, That if Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs doth abound in a Nation, all they are involved in the National Guilt who do not faithfully do their part for the Correction and Reformation of it; and that is, All they, who having any ſufficient Knowledge of any particular of the Offences, do not give due In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation thereof to ſome proper <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> unleſs the Offender will otherwiſe be brought to do what is requiſite. This is evident of it ſelf to any Man of Senſe and Reaſon; and it is further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Authority of the Sacred Scriptures, with reſpect, both to the particular Perſons Offending, and to the Land, and whole Community of the Nation. <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thy heart. Thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy Neighbour, and not ſuffer Sin upon him,</hi> Lev. 19.17. where <hi>hating</hi> ſignifies any defect of Love, and <hi>not hating</hi> implies a Duty of Love and Charity comprized in this Precept. It is an excellent Direction which is given by our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15, 16, 17. for our Dealing with Offenders. So that the firſt thing to be intended and endeavoured, is the Good of the Offender, the Gaining of our Brother. But if he be incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible by private Admonition, then muſt Application be made to Authority, not only for his Correction, but for the Removing or Preventing ſo much of the Evil from the Nation, and to avoid any Participation in the common Guilt. But it is further to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, that it is not only the Perſon Offending, the Perſon privy to the Offence, and the whole Community that is concerned in it, but, (which is, and ought to be, to all who have any Senſe of Religion, more than all) the Honour of God, whoſe Laws are contemned. And if Devotion, in ſuch caſe, be not enough to incite to Action; Senſe and Apprehenſion of Judgment, for Neglect of Duty, if there be cauſe for that, poſſibly may. And if the Zeal of <hi>Phinehas,</hi> in the Cauſe of God, was ſo acceptable, that it procured the Averting of Judgment from the People, and a Bleſſing upon himſelf; the Neglect of Duty, and Unfaithfulneſs of a Perſon in ſuch a Caſe, may provoke Judgment, either here, at leaſt to be left out to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in ſome common Judgment, or hereafter. <hi>Conceilment,</hi> in ſome Caſes, is Criminal, and Puniſhable by the Laws of Men;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151756:6"/>but in many others it may be culpable by the Laws of God, and bring Judgment upon the Guilty; and the Ancient Chriſtians did puniſh it according to the Nature of the Crime or Offence conceiled: And, if I be not much miſtaken, it is an epidemical Sin in this Nation at this time: for inſtance, What is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at the Tables of Noble Men and Gentlemen, and in all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, than Prophanation of the Holy Name of GOD? and, What more rare to be met with than any Proſecution, or ſo much as Reproof for the ſame? And if we enquire into the Reaſons, we ſhall find none but what are reducible to Fear, or Shame; which are more horrid Sins than is commonly apprehended. <hi>The Fear of Man bringeth a Snare: but whoſo putteth his Truſt in the Lord ſhall be ſafe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi> But it is a diſmal Snare, which is detected in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> where we find <hi>the Fearful</hi> placed in the Front with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers, Abominable,</hi> and the reſt that ſhall <hi>have their part in the Lake which burneth with Fire and Brimſtone,</hi> Rev. 21.8. and to the ſame effect it is which our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Mar.</hi> 8.38. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall be aſhamed of me, and of my Words, in this adulterous and ſinful Generation, of him alſo the Son of Man ſhall be aſhamed, when he cometh in the Glory of his Father, with the holy Angels.</hi> And if the Caſes be juſtly examined, the difference of the Temptations of thoſe who lapſed in the Times of Perſecution, and of thoſe who fear, or are aſhamed to open their Mouths in the Cauſe of God now, when they have the Laws on their ſide, I do not ſee any reaſon to think the Sin of theſe ever a jot leſs than that of thoſe, which, amongſt the Ancient Chriſtians, was reckoned one of the firſt Rank. And if this be ſo, what a load of Guilt doth lye upon this Nation upon the ſcore of this one particular. So that both the Greatneſs of the Sin in it ſelf, and the Greatneſs of the Guilt already contracted upon the Nation by this Unfaithfulneſs, both to God, and to our Countrey, are ſuch as may reaſonably move conſiderate Perſons to beware of them, that they do not, by any Neglect, partake in them. Beſides, <hi>the Promiſes of the Goſpel</hi> to ſuch as <hi>ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake,</hi> Mat. 5.10, 11, 12. 1 Pet. 4.15. are ſuch as greatly aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the Sin of ſuch a Neglect, and of the Neglect of ſuch an Occaſion of acquiring a Title to ſuch Promiſes, were the Sufferings certain, and much greater than can reaſonably be feared now. But a great part of the Suffering now to be fear'd is but a Bugbear, and hath nothing real in it, that is the Reproach of being <hi>Informer.</hi> It is true, the uſual Practice of Informers, for Malice or Lucre, hath brought an evil Name upon what is not only a thing indifferent in its own Nature, but well uſed, both Lawful, Neceſſary, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151756:6"/>When Men do it not out of Malice, or for Lucre, but for the real Good of the Offender, of the Community, and for the Honour and Service of God, this is an Act of Charity, and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and truly Honourable.</p>
            <p>This which I have ſaid concerning the Obligations of <hi>all, who have any Knowledge</hi> of any Offences againſt the Laws, to give Information thereof to ſuch as have Authority to correct and puniſh the ſame, is no leſs Obligatory upon <hi>all in Authority</hi> to proceed, according to their Information. Nay, if they, through Fear or Shame, (which doth too often happen; through the Impudence of this moſt wicked Generation) neglect their Duty therein, their Guilt is much greater, they having, in a manner, the Law in their own hand, and being ſo eſpecially obliged, as before is ſhewed.</p>
            <p>And here I ſhall recommend one Conſideration more to all ſuch as truly and cordially deſire to diſcharge the Duty, not only of common Humanity, or of a civil State, but of Chriſtians indeed: they muſt conſider farther, that though this be a <hi>Chriſtian State,</hi> yet is the whole Nation in a very <hi>ſinful State,</hi> and hath great reaſon to fear ſome very ſevere <hi>Judgment of God</hi> for the Puniſhment and Correction thereof. If we well conſider the Judgments of God threatned, both in the Old and the New Teſtament, and the ſevere Judgments of God executed upon the Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which were his peculiar People, and now are, and have been for many Ages, a Monument of his Judgments to all others; upon the Seven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſo Famous heretofore; upon the former flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other <hi>Greek</hi> Churches, now under miſerable Slavery; upon the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Church, which was one of the firſt and beſt Reformed Churches; and others; and then conſider the preſent<note n="*" place="margin">The O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> ſpreading <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> full Groth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> Sin &amp; W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Nation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the approa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> of Gods Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, briefly no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in the Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Publick F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> State of this Church and Nation, how little any of theſe have exceeded us in Wickedneſs; and how little Effect either the Judgments or the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God have had upon us, toward a Reformation; We may ſee great reaſon to expect the like Judgments near approaching now, and no reaſon to hope to eſcape the ſame, without a very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Reformation of that horrid Wickedneſs which is daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by a great part; to ſay nothing of the Pride and Vanity, the Covetouſneſs and Wordly-mindedneſs, the Formality and Luke-warmneſs, and other Decays of genuine Chriſtian Piety and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, even in Profeſſors of Religion, which are things out of the reach of Humane Laws.</p>
            <p>The former Conſiderations manifeſt a <hi>general Obligation</hi> upon all, to uſe their beſt Endeavours for the Good of their Countrey, and our ſelves, but this a <hi>more ſpecial Obligation</hi> to be active upon Neceſſity,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151756:7"/>for Preſervation from imminent Judgment and Deſtruction, or great Calamity, that we be not ſurprized in it: for it is very plain and evident, that the greateſt part of the Nation is at this time, from the higheſt to the loweſt, under ſuch a ſpirit of Slumber, Senſeleſneſs, and Careleſneſs, as doth uſually preceed ſuch ſurprizing Judgments, and whereof our Saviour gave great Warning, as we may read, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.24, 36. (which is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, not only of his Goming at the laſt great Day, but alſo of his Coming in Judgment upon particular Nations and Churches) and in other places of the Goſpels. But in the Severeſt of his Judgments the Merciful and Gracious God doth always, by a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing Providence, which is noted by our Saviour, and is very obſervable in all the Prophetick Denunciations of Judgments, and in the Execution thereof, ſecure <hi>a Remnant</hi> of ſuch as ſincerely fear Him, and ſeek to avert his Judgments. So that there is great <hi>Encouragement</hi> for thoſe who will take Warning, and endeavour to be of that Number, whatever become of the reſt. But if they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour that as they ought, there is hopes that Judgment may be averted from all. For, to paſs by other Reaſons, what we have ſeen effected by the Zeal and Activity of one Man, we may well hope may much more be effected by the Zeal and concurrent Activity of many. In the Sacred Hiſtory we have a remarkable Inſtance of the Judgments of God and the fierce Anger of the Lord turned away from the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by the Courage and Activity of one, <hi>Phinehas,</hi> while he was Zealous for God's Sake among them, ſo that the Plague was ſtayed from them, that he conſumed them not in his Jealouſie. Becauſe he was Zealous for God, and thereby made an Attonement for the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he at once both pacified the Wrath of God, and ſo averted his Judgment from them, and alſo obtained a ſpecial Glorious Promiſe and Bleſſing of God for himſelf, and his Poſterity, as we may ſee, <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>There are <hi>other Duties</hi> incumbent upon all, in reſpect of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, which we have great Reaſon to fear; as Repentance, and Reformation of our ſelves, and Mourning and Supplication for the Sins of the Nation, and frequent and earneſt Prayers for the Averting of thoſe Judgments: but that which here was to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, is only the Promotion of a Reformation by a vigorous and ſteddy Execution of Laws; which reſpects both this, and all the reſt of the Obligations before mentioned; of this more might be ſaid; but theſe things well conſider'd, I ſuppoſe <hi>ſufficient,</hi> as to the Execution of the Laws in general: But I muſt add a few things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning one in particular, which was the Occaſion of this Diſcourſe. It is,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:151756:7"/>
                  <head>The Late ACT for the more effectual Suppreſſing Prophane CURSING and SWEARING, To this Effect.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat if any Perſon, after</hi> 24 June, 1695. <hi>prophanely Swear or Curſe in the Preſence of any Juſtice of the Peace, or Head Officer of the Place where the Offence is committed, or ſhall be thereof convicted by the Oath of</hi> One Witneſs, <hi>or by his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſion before ſuch Juſtice or Officer, be ſhall for every ſuch Offence</hi> Pay <hi>to the Vſe of the Poor of the Pariſh, where the Offence is committed, if Servant, Day-Labourer, Common Souldier, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Seaman, One Shilling, and every other Perſon Two Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; and for a</hi> Second Offence <hi>after Conviction, double; and for</hi> a Third, <hi>treble.</hi> 2. <hi>That upon</hi> Neglect or Refuſal to Pay, <hi>any ſuch Juſtice or Officer ſhall ſend his Warrant to the Conſtable, Tything-Man, Church-Warden, or Overſeer of the Poor of the Pariſh, where the Offence is committed,</hi> to Levy <hi>the Sum forfeited to the Vſe of the Poor of the Pariſh; and in caſe</hi> no Diſtreſs <hi>can be had, to ſet the Offender, if above the Age of Sixteen, in the Stocks by the ſpace of one Hour, for a ſingle Offence; and for more than one Offence, at the ſame time, two Hours: but if under that Age, unleſs he Pay forthwith, to cauſe him to be</hi> Whip'd <hi>by the Conſtable, or by the Parent, Guardian, or Maſter of the Offender, in the Preſence of the Conſtable.</hi> 3. <hi>That if the Juſtice or Officer wilfully or wittingly</hi> omit the Pertormance <hi>of this Duty in the Execution of this Act, be ſhall Forfeit Five Pounds, one Moiety to the Vſe of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former.</hi> 4. <hi>That if any</hi> Suit <hi>be brought againſt any Juſtice, Officer, or Perſon, for any thing done in purſuance of this Act, the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant may Plead the General Iſſue, and give the Special Matter in Evidence, and ſhall have treble Coſts, upon Verdict for him, or the Plaintiffs Nonſuit or Diſcontinuance.</hi> 5. Proviſo <hi>that the Proof be within ten Days next after the Offence committed.</hi> 6. <hi>That the Act be</hi> Read in all Churches <hi>and</hi> Publick Chappels <hi>immediately after Morning Prayer on Four Sundays,</hi> viz. <hi>next after</hi> June 24. Septemb. 29. Dec. 25. <hi>and</hi> March 25. <hi>under pain of Twenty Shillings for every Omiſſion.</hi> 7. <hi>That the Juſtice or Head-Officer</hi> Regiſter <hi>all Convictions at the time, and</hi> Certifie <hi>the ſame at the next General Quarter Seſſions, to be kept upon Record, to be ſeen without Fee.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:151756:8"/>
            <p> The Deſign of this ACT, Is to puniſh, correct and ſuppreſs two common Offences againſt the Two great Commandments of God. The one, <hi>viz. Prophane</hi> SWEARING, is a Crime immediately againſt the Sacred Majeſty and Holineſs of Almighty God; a Crime, for which the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> here preſcribed is no way propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable, either in reſpect of God, or Man; and, therefore, ought the more ſtrictly to be Executed: A Crime againſt the Common Parent, Lord, and Great Benefactor of Mankind; and, therefore, ought, by all Men, much more to be reſented than any Indignity offered to our Natural Parents, or to any Humane Benefactors; which, to neglect, is uſually reputed great Baſeneſs: A Crime of the greateſt Inconſiderateneſs, Vanity, and Baſeneſs of Mind; <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderateneſs,</hi> ſo to tranſgreſs the Laws of God and Man; to give Example of Diſorder, and Violation of Laws to others; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict himſelf, his Profeſſion of Belief of a Deity, and the Chriſtian Religion, and his Pretence to Loyalty, and Regard to his Countrey; to expoſe his Reputation, and, by his own Example, to provoke the Indignation of others, and encourage Rudeneſs, Diſ-reſpect, and Affronts to himſelf; and all this, with ſo much <hi>Vanity</hi> as many do, upon ſo mean a Motive as an affected Ornament of Speech and Gallantry, which is, to Glory in his Shame: and, beſides, with ſo much <hi>Baſeneſs of Spirit,</hi> as many do, even contrary to the Dictates of their Conſcience, in Compliance with ſuch inconſiderate and vain Perſons, for fear of Reproach, little Cenſures, or Contempt from them: or through Impotence, which cannot overcome ſo unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable a Habit, or evil Cuſtom: Laſtly, A Crime ſo <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnatural, and intirely Diabolical,</hi> without any Natural Diſpoſition to it, but meerly of Diabolical Impreſſion, that the Common Swearer may reaſonably be reputed an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Aſſociate with that Curſed Prophane Company of Witches, and Confederates with the Devil, and ought to be abhorred by all Sober People, and Puniſhed in the next degree to that accurſed Crew. And if we farther conſider how common this Diabolical and Abominable Sin is amongſt us, not only among the Ruder and Baſer Sort, as they are reputed, but even among thoſe who have had, what is commonly reputed, the greateſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Education; and how impudent, to be looked upon as a matter of Gallantry, and to be gloried in; we muſt conclude it, if we will judge impartially, the <hi>Shame</hi> of the State in theſe late Reigns, the Shame of the Magiſtrates, the Shame of the Clergy, and the Shame of the People and Nation; and one of thoſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties for which <hi>the Land Mourneth,</hi> Jer. 23.10. And if, beſides all the Obligations before-mentioned to Execute the Laws in general
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151756:8"/>againſt all Offences, all that is here ſaid concerning this in Particular be not ſufficient to raiſe Indignation and Zeal in all, both Magiſtrates and People, and every one, as they have Occaſion, for the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and Extirpation of ſo Unnatural, Diabolical, and Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Crime, I muſt leave them to bear their Iniquity by the Judgment of God. <hi>If a Soul Sin, and hear the Voice of Swearing, and is a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs whether he hath ſeen or known of it, if he do not utter it, then he ſhall bear his Iniquity,</hi> Levit. 5.1.</p>
            <p>But theſe things, I hope, will be more largely preſſed by <hi>the Clergy,</hi> when the ACT is read in the Church, as it is ordered to be four times in the Year, under a certain Penalty. For, certainly, it would be doubly Shameful, if their Preaching, with ſuch Aſſiſtance of the Civil Authority, ſhould not be able to ſuppreſs ſo impious, ſo unreaſonable, ſo unnatural and diabolical a Crime, which hath ſo little Temptation in Nature, or from any Natural Diſpoſition to ſtrengthen or ſupport it: and I cannot think any Man fit to hold a Cure of Souls, who will permit any ſuch Crime committed in his Pariſh to eſcape unpuniſhed, if he know it, or can have Proof to convict the Offender. And, to that purpoſe, it will be neceſſary, not only to Preach againſt the Sin, but alſo to preſs the Duty of Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to ſuppreſs it.</p>
            <p>If any <hi>Member of Parliament</hi> ſhould preſume upon his <hi>Priviledge,</hi> it is to be remembred: 1. That Information to a Magiſtrate againſt a Member of Parliament for this Offence, is no Breach of Priviledge. 2. Nor is a Warrant by a Juſtice of the Peace to demand the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture. 3. Or a Demand of the Forfeiture by an Officer, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Warrant. But if the Forfeiture be not paid, the Magiſtrate may make another Warrant to diſtrain when the Time of Priviledge is out, or, in the mean time, upon juſt Occaſion ſend up the Warrant, with the Conſtables or Church-Wardens Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, to the Parliament. And this may be very fit to be done when the Offence is committed with ſuch aggravating Circumſtances, as manifeſt it to be done wilfully and preſumptuouſly: For that being a Contempt of the Laws, and, by Conſequence, of the Authority by which they are made; and which is far above all, of the Sacred Majeſty of Almighty God, whoſe Miniſters, Legiſlators, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates are, it is very fit to be well conſider'd, whether ſuch a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be fit to be permitted to ſit in Parliament, or to be admitted to any Publick Employment in a Chriſtian State?</p>
            <p>To conclude, What from theſe Principles is demonſtrated neceſſary to be done, is from Experience, and particularly of what was done in <hi>the late <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> very evident that it is practicable, and may
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151756:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>he done again. We have ſeen this abominable Sin of Prophane <hi>Swearing</hi> and <hi>Curſing,</hi> and the <hi>Prophanation</hi> of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>'s Day,</hi> and thoſe Brutiſh Sins of <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> and <hi>notorious Debauchery,</hi> ſo ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in thoſe times in all Places of the Nation, that nothing can be more Scandalous in a Legal Government, than that they ſhould have revived under it to ſuch a Growth and Impudence. If the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration of the Legal Government produce ſuch Effects, as the Reſtauration of ſuch <hi>Licentiouſneſs, Wickedneſs,</hi> and <hi>Debauchery,</hi> and no better, it is not like to recommend it either to God, or to Man; but be a Temptation to Man, as well as a Provocation to God, to concur to a Change; and therefore it concerns both the Governours, and all who wiſh well to the Government, to look well to it; to remember what Revolutions and Confuſions have proceeded in other States from ſuch Occaſions, and take care, by an effectual Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, to prevent the like here in time. And if that will not, the <hi>preſent Example</hi> of our potent Neighbour and Enemy ought to move us to a <hi>Godly Jealouſie,</hi> leſt he not only get the Palm of Victory, but alſo take our Crown from us, by the Favour of God, if he be found more forward, active, reſolute and faithful in the Reformation of ſuch Wickedneſs amongſt his People, than we, who pretend to a more Reformed Religion, are here. Nay, our very <hi>Publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, His Majeſty's Letter to the Biſhops of</hi> 13 Feb, 1689/90. and <hi>His Proclamation</hi> 21 Jan. 1691/2. may riſe in Judgment againſt us, as Evidence of our Unfaithfulneſs in the Service of God, of our Trifling with his Holy Majeſty, and wilful Neglect of known and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Duty. And that wicked Practice which was uſed to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt that Hopeful Reformation begun upon <hi>Her Majeſty's Letter to the Juſtices of Mtddleſex,</hi> 9 July, 1691. and the Indignity done to Her, certainly will receive a juſt Recompence of Reward. Theſe things may bring Evil upon the whole, but eſpecially upon them, at whoſe door the Fault doth lye: But true Zeal for this Service may prevent the Evil from the whole, but eſpecially from them, who are Faithful therein.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
